Hello, everyone.
Welcome to our second
lecture on respiratory
physiology.
Today, we're going to talk
about diffusion of gases
through the
respiratory membrane.
My name is Dr. Jörg LeHest.
These learning objectives
are consistent with
the event description,
which is that it focuses
on the principles
behind the mechanisms of
gas exchange based on the
fundamental properties
of gases and their
behavior and solution.
The fundamental laws
of physics governing
these processes
will be explored.
Let's begin with the
general gas law, which is
described as P, which is
pressure, times volume,
that's V, equaling N, which
is the number of molecules
in moles, times R,
which is a gas constant
specific for each type of
gas, times the temperature.
So there's a relationship,
in other words, between
pressure and volume and
number of gas molecules
and a couple of other
factors. Let's explore.
So here we have the
standard propane gas tank
that everybody knows with
gas molecules inside,
which is depicted here
on the right. And due
to Brownian motion, these
molecules are moving
around and bumping into
each other. That is what
is reducing the pressure
inside the cylinder.
So if we assume that the
volume is constant in the
cylinder, we can take out
the V here in our formula. So
what remains is that the
pressure is a function of the
number of gas molecules
times the constant times
temperature. So in other words,
what can we do to alter the
pressure? Well we can either
go to the refilling station
and add more gas so that
will increase the pressure,
or we can move the cylinder
from a cool, dry space
where it's supposed to be
into the sun, and that would
also increase the pressure
because of the temperature.
So how does this
matter to the human
body? Well, for the
human body, we assume
BTPS. That stands
for body temperature,
ambient pressure, and
saturation with water.
So for human purposes, or
for medical purposes, we
assume that the gas is at
37 degrees Celsius. That's
310 degrees Kelvin, so that's
normal body temperature.
We assume ambient pressure,
and we further assume
that the gas is saturated
with water vapor.
So that's exactly the
condition that the gas is
in that resides in our
lungs. It's at body
temperature. It's at
ambient pressure. so there
are no huge pressure
differences between inside
and outside, and there
is a lot of water vapor.
Sometimes it becomes
important to standardize
things further. Then
we consider the STPD.
So for that, we assume a
standard temperature, which
is zero degrees Celsius,
that's 273 Kelvin. in.
We utilize the standard
pressure which is at sea
level 760 millimeters mercury
and further on we assume
that the gas is dry. That
simplifies things a lot.
This is Boyle's law and
Boyle's law considers that the
product of pressure and
volume of a gas is constant.
So that of course since
we already know from the
previous slide that temperature
plays a role has to assume
that the temperature
is constant. So it says
basically that the pressure
and volume of this container
here on the left is the
same as the pressure volume
product of the
container in the right.
So how is that possible?
Well pressure and volume
are inversely
proportional. So in other
words if the volume
goes down that would be
according to the red
arrow, the pressure
goes up, so they're
inversely proportional.
Conversely, if the volume goes
up, so the volume increases,
then the pressure goes
down. That makes sense
because all of these gas
molecules are bumping into
each other much less and
that reduces the pressure.
So while the pressure and
volumes in both containers
are vastly different,
their product is the same.
So that's what this law
says. And how does this
matter? Well, our
breathing is rhythmical, so
we breathe in and we
breathe out, and that's only
possible due to pressure
volume differences.
So we all know that if
we take a breath, the
volume of our rib cage
has to expand so that
reduces the pressure
inside, making the air from
the outside flowing
into our lungs. If we
breathe out, if we expire,
the opposite happens.
And so all of this is
governed by Boyle's
Law, and that's how
Boyle's Law matters.
This is Dalton's Law,
and Dalton's Law says
that the pressure of a
mix of gases consists
of a product of the
partial pressures of all
of the gases in that
particular container.
So in other words,
the partial pressure of one
gas in this mix is equal
to its pressure at
barometric pressure, that's
Pb, times the fractional
concentration of the gas.
And in physiological
context, this
is corrected for
by water vapor,
so Dalton's law then
becomes the partial pressure
of a gas equaling the pressure
of the gas at barometric
pressure minus the
pressure of the water vapor
times the fractional
proportion of the gas.
And if one survives at the
total gas pressure of this
mix of gases, one has to
add up all of these partial
pressures and produce a sum
of them, and that sum has to
equal the total pressure
of that particular mixture.
So partial pressure is
sometimes really difficult to
work with, especially in a
medical diagnostic the context.
So we need some form of
equation that allows us to
convert the partial pressure
of a gas into a concentration
in blood, in liquid phase
in this case. And that
is exactly what Henry's law
is doing. So it converts
the partial pressure into
milliliters of gas per 100
milliliters of blood, or we
can also use percentages.
So in order to do this,
we have to multiply
the partial pressure of
a gas with its solubility
in blood in this case,
and then arrive in
it with a number of
dissolved gas in blood.
What's really important
to consider when talking
about Henry's law is
that this only applies to
gases that are free in
solution, so which we
already know is very little
for oxygen, because most
of the oxygen is bind
to hemoglobin. There's
only very little that is
not bound to hemoglobin.
And it applies much more
so for carbon dioxide,
because a lot of the carbon
dioxide, actually majority,
is transported in a soluble
form, either dissolved
directly as CO2 or as
part of bicarbonate buffer
system, and both contribute
to the partial pressure.
So in other words, only a
gas that is dissolved in a
solution, such as blood,
contributes to the partial
pressure. Gases that are bound
to proteins such as hemoglobin
or albumin, they're not
considered as part of a
partial pressure. they don't
exert a partial pressure.
Fick's law considers
the diffusion of gases,
and so it considers the
volume of gas that is
transferred per unit of time,
that's what Vx stands for,
and it equals the
diffusion coefficient of a
gas, so that's different
for different gases,
times the surface area,
times the partial pressure
gradient of that gas, divided
by the thickness of the
membrane. So right away you
should see that this part
of the equation contains all
of the components that we
find in alveoli where gas
exchange actually occurs.
Another thing that I would
like to mention is that
the diffusion coefficient
for gases is much,
much larger for CO2, about
50 times as high as it
is for O2. So in other
words, it's much easier
to get CO2 into solution
or into blood as oxygen.
So in other words, again,
carbon dioxide is
much more soluble in
blood and water as
a fact as oxygen.
Now, a very handy consideration
is the lung diffusion
capacity, or DI, because
it doesn't really help
us all that much to only
consider gases that are
free in solution, and
that as delta P describes,
are part of a partial
pressure gradient. So
we need to also look
at gases that bind to
proteins because a
lot of the oxygen, for
instance, is bound to
hemoglobin, and some of the
carbon dioxide is also
bound to hemoglobin.
So the lung diffusion
capacity, or DI,
it does that. So it combines
the diffusion coefficient
of gas, it considers the
surface area, it considers
the thickness of the
membrane between an alveolar
capillary and the alveolar
space that is filled with air.
But it also considers, in
addition to Fick's law, it
not only considers gases
that are free in solution, it
also considers gases that
are bound to protein. So that
is a much more accurate
physiological consideration.
So the lung diffusion
capacity basically
describes how easy
it is for gases
to cross from one
medium into the next,
or how easy it is to cross
from the alveolar space
into the alveolar
capillaries, or vice versa.
And these are all the
factors that contribute.
So for instance, red
blood cells matter because
under conditions of
anemia, then there are less
red blood cells, so
there is maybe a lot of
oxygen inside the alveolus.
But since there is
less molecules that can
pick up the oxygen, then
that influences the
lung diffusion capacity.
Same with alveoli and
capillaries, depending on what
their condition is in
terms of cell density, cell
number that influences the
lung diffusion capacity.
One thing that we'll
consider later in this
portion of the course are
pathologic conditions.
So fibrosis, for instance,
and also endema, they kind
of increase the distance
between the alveolar and the
capillary component and
make it more difficult for
gases to cross from one from
one realm into the other
and so forth so here we have
a standard arterial blood
gas which is commonly
assessed as part of clinical
laboratory medicine which
tells us a lot about what
the gases are and concentrations
that are dissolved so
that is what the oxygen
content for instance will do
how much of gases are
bound to proteins for
instance that's what the
O2 sat will do so because
it considers oxygenated
hemoglobin and also
how gases may have been
chemically modified So
we're looking at pH,
partial pressure of CO2,
partial pressure of
O2, and then here again
the bicarbonate buffer
system. So this is
bicarbonate, and that
information can all be
obtained from a standard
arterial blood gas.
This is a very simple
depiction of how gas exchange
in the lungs occurs. So
here is the site of gas
exchange at the alveoli,
blood comes in through
the pulmonary circuit in
the form of venous blood
from the right heart, then
gas exchange occurs, oxygen
is moved into the pulmonary
capillary blood and
CO2 is being removed, it
goes into the alveolus,
and then it leaves freshly
oxygenated going back into
the left heart and then
into the systemic circuit
so let's put some numbers
two things so the partial
pressure of ambient outside
air is of oxygen is about
160 millimeters mercury
there's hardly any carbon
dioxide in that air we're
working really hard as
humans to change that and
make that number significant
as the air moves down the
trachea it's being humidified
there's also mixed air
in here so there's a dead
space which is incompressible
you've discussed that
in one of the previous
lectures by the end of it
once it reaches once that
air reaches the alveolar
space it only has a partial
pressure of oxygen of around
100 and since it has
already picked up the carbon
dioxide that partial pressure
is now at 40 and then
it moves like that into
the systemic circuit um
just as a heads up some books
have this number here at
slightly higher than 100
so it's between 105 and 108
but then it's at the
arterial and the partial
pressure of oxygen in the
arterial arteries, I'm sorry,
is still 100. That's
because of shunting. So
remember that part of the
brachial circuit is shunted
back and mixed into the
freshly oxygenated blood.
And so even if the blood
initially, as it crosses
here, has a higher
partial pressure than 100,
namely 105 to 8,
it'll be lowered due
to the contribution
of deoxygenated blood
coming in from the
brachial circuit.
This slide here depicts
an important concept,
and it depicts the concepts
of diffusion versus
perfusion limited gas
exchange so in other words
how quickly a gas can
equilibrate between the
alveolar space into
which it has been taken
up through breathing
that's the green line here
with the concentration
that's found in the pulmonary
capillary that is supposed
to take up that gas that's
this line here so if you
look here then this y
-axis is the concentration
or partial pressure of this
gas. And as the pulmonary
capillary runs across the
pulmonary alveolar space
longer and longer, it
picks up more and more
gas. But in this example
here with carbon monoxide,
it never reaches the
concentration of carbon
monoxide found in the
pulmonary alveolar space.
And in a situation like
that, we're talking about
diffusion limitation.
So why is that the case
with carbon monoxide?
Well, if you remember
partial pressure, and that's
from the earlier part of the
lecture, it depends on how
much gas is dissolved in
this case in the pulmonary
capillary bloodstream so gases
that are bound to proteins
such as hemoglobin or
albumin they don't count so
and one of the features of
carbon monoxide which also
makes it so dangerous
is that as it enters the
bloodstream it immediately binds
to hemoglobin so that means
it never exists much in
its dissolved form in blood
therefore it doesn't
participate in the partial
pressure equation so that's
why as per partial pressure
the concentration of dissolved
carbon monoxide can never
reach the partial pressure
in the alveolar space
because before it can dissolve
in the blood, it's already
like a magnet taken up by
the hemoglobin molecule.
A similar situation
we have with
oxygen in two
conditions, the two
physiological and also
pathophysiological
conditions. So during
exercise, for instance,
the oxygen that would be
here in the alveolar space
would always be the oxygen
concentration of the
partial pressure of oxygen
would always be larger
than the partial pressure
of oxygen in the capillary
because it's used up
so quickly with oxygen
dissolving in blood so
poorly that this difference
will always exist. Remember
that oxygen is much
harder to dissolve in the
liquid phase, water or blood,
compared to carbon
monoxide or carbon dioxide.
Carbon monoxide is a
special case because it does
dissolve well in blood, but
it binds to right away to
hemoglobin, so it does not
factor into the partial pressure
equation the same thing we
have in pathophysiological
conditions fibrosis and
emphysema so fibrosis is
marked by the thickening of
the epithelium that separates
this space from that
space and if the capillary
epithelium if that epithelium
human epithelium is thicker,
then oxygen in this case,
which is already a poor
diffuser, has even a harder
time perfusing or diffusing
from the alveolar space
into the surrounding
capillary. With emphysema,
it's a little bit different,
but similar. Instead of
fibrotic thickening, we see
destruction of cells and
emphysema and that also provides
the gases that have to
diffuse across from one
phase in the pulmonary alveolar
space into the capillary
with less opportunity to
do so and hence we are
looking at a diffusion
limited situation now
with nitric oxide it's a
little bit different and
And in this case, we
have a high concentration
in the alveolar space
right here, and as blood
enters the pulmonary
capillary, it pretty much
right away equilibrates,
and the concentration in
the blood reaches the
same level as that of the
ambient air, which sits
in the alveolar space.
that's how it happens
under normal physiological
conditions with oxygen and
carbon dioxide so there's a
lot of leeway built in in
other words our system has
equilibrated the oxygen and
the carbon dioxide under
normal physiological conditions
about one third through
blood flow of the pulmonary
capillary through the
alveolar system so it takes
about one third of the
time that the blood has
to flow past the alveolar
space to pick up and
equilibrate completely with the
oxygen and carbon dioxide
concentration of both sides.
And that situation is called
perfusion limited because
the system that brings
in fresh blood that could
pick up more and more of
those gases and more and more
oxygen and get rid of more
and more carbon dioxide
is just limited by its flow.
So there's a certain flow
rate to which, remember
it's a low pressure system,
the pulmonary
capillary bloodstream
moves and that is
the limiting factor
here. To illustrate how
diffusion can be limited by
pathology, so on the left
we have the same type of
graph with partial pressure,
in this case oxygen,
in the alveoli versus
the concentration
of oxygen along
the capillary bed.
So under normal conditions
at the beginning of the
capillary bed, because the
oxygen that comes there is
never oxygen free so it
has a partial pressure as
it comes into the pulmonary
circulation of around 45
millimeters mercury along
it takes about one third
of travel through the
capillary network until the
blood is completely
equilibrated with the oxygen
concentration in the pulmonary
alveoli and fibrosis because
of the additional
diffusion barrier due to a
thicker basal membrane that
equilibration never happens
and depending on the degree
of fibrosis that individual
might never reach the
100 millimeters mercury
in oxygen as compared to
the normal situation things
get even worse under
conditions of high altitude so
at the very high
highest points on this
planet the partial
pressure of oxygen may
only be around 50
millimeters mercury and
so for a person with
normal lung function
the reduced gradient you
can see that the gradient
here is less than the gradient
here sorry the gradient
here so this gradient
here is much larger which
accelerates this process of
equilibration the gradient
here is smaller so for
the pulmonary capillary
blood to take up all of
the oxygen that is in the
alveolar space it just
takes a little bit more time
but in the end it'll get
there and the fibrotic
conditions due to the extra
diffusion length diffusion
barrier that process not
only takes longer but is
very likely never to fully
occur so somebody in other
words who is suffering
from a fibrotic condition
has problems already at
sea level where the partial
pressure of oxygen as it
reaches the alveoli is 100
under more extreme
conditions this person
might not even be able
to survive due to the
transport deficiency
of oxygen from the
alveoli air into their
pulmonary bloodstream.
And in the end,
another practice
medical board style
question for you.
A clinical physiology
researcher is testing alveolar
gas equilibration in a
healthy 25-year-old athlete
performing maximum intense
knee treadmill exercise.
During intense exercise,
the velocity of cardiac
output increased
significantly, reducing the
transit time of an
individual erythrocyte
through the alveolar
capillary from a resting time
of three quarters to
a quarter of a second.
Under normal physiological
conditions, how does
this short and transit
time affect the capillary
equilibration of oxygen
and what type of transport
limit does this demonstrate?
So this gets right
at the most challenging
topic of this election uh
lecture and i give you
some time to look at the
answer choices you
can also stop the recording to
look at them a
little bit longer
um so what i would always
like you to do is not just
go for the prize but also
understand and question why
the distractors may be
incorrect so let's go through
them one by one a oxygen
transport becomes diffusion
limited because the shortened
transit time prevents the
partial pressure of capillary
oxygen from matching
alveolar levels so under
normal physiological conditions
that does not happen
because at sea level in a
healthy individual without
any diseases the transit time
is about a quarter of a
second so in other words it
takes the oxygen um about
a quarter of a second to be
fully equilibrated between
the alveolar space and the
capillary blood that flows
through the lungs and in a
healthy person that should
be all the time that it
takes so if anything um
blood i'm sorry the uptake of
of of oxygen is perfusion
limited so what that means is
that the amount that can
be taken up depends on how
fast the blood can be pumped
through the lungs so that's
perfusion limitation so
it's not diffusion limited
because there's no additional
barriers and in a healthy
individual as i said this
should all happen within
the allotted time okay so
a is incorrect let's go to
see oxygen transport
switches from being diffusion
limited because carbon
dioxide competes for the same
capillary surface area during
intense exercise now that's
obviously incorrect because
oxygen and carbon dioxide
don't really compete in
that way they bind to
different sites on hemoglobin
and yeah so that makes c
incorrect d oxygen transport
becomes perfusion limited
because the high velocity
of blood flow prevents any
gas diffusion from taking
place across the blood brain
blood air barrier so
the first part of the
statement you know it's
still incorrect because
it has always been
perfusion limited in a
healthy individual, so
it doesn't become that.
And if anything, the increased
blood flow through the
lungs actually increases the
pickup capacity of oxygen
from the alveolar space. So
that makes the incorrect.
E oxygen transport remains
diffusion limited because
the thickening of the
blood barrier plane barrier
blood air barrier i'm a
neuroscientist sorry about that
during exercise slows down
the physiological movement
of gas molecules so there's
no thickening going on
during intense exercise
because if there were diffusion
time would terribly increase
we would never be able
to exercise so in a healthy
individual that does
not happen and somebody
however who is suffering from
fibrosis there is actual
sickening going on and there
we experience the fusion
limitation as we have seen
in in the lecture before
so the correct answer
is b oxygen transport
becomes perfusion limited
because partial pressure
equilibration is reached
well within the shortened
25 or quarter second window
so i would still argue
that um becomes i wouldn't
use becomes necessarily so
i could have probably um
i should have used is
perfusion limited or remains
perfusion limited but don't
let that throw you off
so let's just say in an
individual in a healthy
condition oxygen transport
is always perfusion limited
um at sea level um where
would that not be the case
well of course at higher
levels and at higher
altitudes we have less
oxygen in the air in
the ambient air so there
it can actually become
oxygen uptake can
become an issue all
right I hope that
helps and look at the
resources afterwards
and see you next time
So this was the lecture.
Thank you for listening.
Please be reminded that
all of the resources that
I used for creating this
lecture are listed on the
CPG, so I'm staying very
closely to the chapter in
Constanzo that talks about
respiratory physiology.
There's, once again, a nice
summary section attached
with it, which I would
recommend you read. Plus,
there are self-testing
questions tied to each chapter.
They're not medical board
style, but, you know, they
do test all of the basic
concepts that we talked
about, so they're very
helpful, and the resolution or
the answers to those
questions can be found at the
end of the book. And if
you have further questions,
you can, of course,
always reach out to me,
and I'd be happy to answer
them. So, thank you.
If you would be so
kind, then please go to
SurveyMonkey and give
me your feedback so that
tell me what you liked,
tell me what needs to
change, and I will take
that very seriously and
adapt and have it ready
for the next cohort.
So thank you once again
and looking forward
to interacting with
you the next time. Bye.